<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Storage on blog.oddbit.com</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/storage/</link><description>Recent content in Storage on blog.oddbit.com</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Lars Kellogg-Stedman</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 10:58:10 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/storage/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Connecting OpenShift to an External Ceph Cluster</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2021-08-23-external-ocs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2021-08-23-external-ocs/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Red Hat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/technologies/cloud-computing/openshift-data-foundation"&gt;OpenShift Data Foundation&lt;/a&gt; (formerly &amp;ldquo;OpenShift
Container Storage&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;OCS&amp;rdquo;) allows you to either (a) automatically
set up a Ceph cluster as an application running on your OpenShift
cluster, or (b) connect your OpenShift cluster to an externally
managed Ceph cluster. While setting up Ceph as an OpenShift
application is a relatively polished experienced, connecting to an
external cluster still has some rough edges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NB&lt;/strong&gt; I am not a Ceph expert. If you read this and think I&amp;rsquo;ve made a
mistake with respect to permissions or anything else, please feel free
to leave a comment and I will update the article as necessary. In
particular, I think it may be possible to further restrict the &lt;code&gt;mgr&lt;/code&gt;
permissions shown in this article and I&amp;rsquo;m interested in feedback on
that topic.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fun with devicemapper snapshots</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2018-01-25-fun-with-devicemapper-snapshot/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2018-01-25-fun-with-devicemapper-snapshot/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I find myself working with &lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/raspbian/"&gt;Raspbian&lt;/a&gt; disk images fairly often. A
typical workflow is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the disk image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mount the filesystem somewhere to check something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make some changes or install packages just to check something else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Crap I&amp;rsquo;ve made changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;at which point I need to fetch a new copy of the image next time I
want to start fresh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, I could just make a copy of the image and work from there, but
what fun is that? This seemed like a perfect opportunity to learn more
about the &lt;a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/device-mapper/"&gt;device mapper&lt;/a&gt; and in particular how the &lt;a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/Documentation/device-mapper/snapshot.txt"&gt;snapshot&lt;/a&gt;
target works.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Growing a filesystem on a virtual disk</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2012-10-24-resizing-virtual-disk/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2012-10-24-resizing-virtual-disk/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Occasionally we will deploy a virtual instance into our KVM
infrastructure and realize after the fact that we need more local disk
space available. This is the process we use to expand the disk image.
This process assumes the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re using legacy disk partitions. The process for LVM is similar
and I will describe that in another post (it&amp;rsquo;s generally identical
except for an additional &lt;code&gt;pvresize&lt;/code&gt; thrown in and &lt;code&gt;lvextend&lt;/code&gt; in
place of &lt;code&gt;resize2fs&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The partition you need to resize is the last partition on the disk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process will work with either a &lt;code&gt;qcow2&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt; disk image. For
&lt;code&gt;raw&lt;/code&gt; images you can also run &lt;code&gt;fdisk&lt;/code&gt; on the host, potentially saving
yourself a reboot, but that&amp;rsquo;s less convenient for &lt;code&gt;qcow2&lt;/code&gt; format
images.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Installing CrashPlan under FreeBSD 8</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2011-05-22-installing-crashplan-under-fre/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2011-05-22-installing-crashplan-under-fre/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This articles describes how I got &lt;a href="http://crashplan.com/"&gt;CrashPlan&lt;/a&gt; running on my FreeBSD 8(-STABLE) system. &lt;a href="http://kim.scarborough.chicago.il.us/do/nerd/tips/crashplan"&gt;These instructions&lt;/a&gt; by Kim Scarborough were my starting point, but as these were for FreeBSD 7 there were some additional steps necessary to get things working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="install-java"&gt;Install Java&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had originally thought that it might be possible to run the CrashPlan client &amp;ldquo;natively&amp;rdquo; under FreeBSD. CrashPlan is a Java application, so this seemed like a possible solution. Unfortunately, Java under FreeBSD 8 seems to be a lost cause. I finally gave up and just installed Java under Linux.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>