<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>keyboards on blog.oddbit.com</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/keyboards/</link><description>Recent content in keyboards on blog.oddbit.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Lars Kellogg-Stedman</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/keyboards/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Vortex Core Keyboard Review</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2020-09-26-vortex-core-keyboard-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2020-09-26-vortex-core-keyboard-review/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve had my eye on the Vortex Core keyboard for a few months now, and this past week I finally broke down and bought one (with Cherry MX Brown switches). The Vortex Core is a 40% keyboard, which means it consists primarily of letter keys, a few lonely bits of punctuation, and several modifier keys to activate different layers on the keyboard.
Physical impressions It&amp;rsquo;s a really cute keyboard. I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of MX brown switches, and this keyboard is really a joy to type on, at least when you&amp;rsquo;re working primarily with the alpha keys.</description><content>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve had my eye on the &lt;a href="http://www.vortexgear.tw/vortex2_2.asp?kind=47&amp;amp;kind2=224&amp;amp;kind3=&amp;amp;kind4=1033">Vortex Core&lt;/a> keyboard for a few months now, and this
past week I finally broke down and bought one (with Cherry MX Brown switches).
The Vortex Core is a 40% keyboard, which means it consists primarily of letter
keys, a few lonely bits of punctuation, and several modifier keys to activate
different layers on the keyboard.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="physical-impressions">Physical impressions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a really cute keyboard. I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of MX brown switches, and this
keyboard is really a joy to type on, at least when you&amp;rsquo;re working primarily
with the alpha keys. I&amp;rsquo;m still figuring out where some of the punctuation
is, and with a few exceptions I haven&amp;rsquo;t yet spent time trying to remap
things into more convenient positions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The keyboard feels solid. I&amp;rsquo;m a little suspicious of the micro-usb
connector; it feels a little wobbly. I wish that it was USB-C and I wish it
felt a little more stable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s a picture of my Core next to my Durgod &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/DURGOD-Mechanical-Interface-Tenkeyless-Anti-Ghosting/dp/B078H3WPHM">K320&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="left" >
&lt;img src="core-vs-k320.jpg" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h2 id="programming">Programming&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The keyboard first came out in 2017, and if you read reviews that came out
around that time you&amp;rsquo;ll find several complaints around limitations in the
keyboard&amp;rsquo;s programming features, in particular:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>you can&amp;rsquo;t map the left and right spacebars differently&lt;/li>
&lt;li>you can&amp;rsquo;t remap layer 0&lt;/li>
&lt;li>you can&amp;rsquo;t remap the Fn1 key&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>And so forth. Fortunately, at some point (maybe 2018) Vortexgear released
updated firmware that resolves all of the above issues, and introduces a
completely new way of programming the keyboard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Originally, the keyboard was programmed entirely via the keyboard itself: there
was a key combination to activate programming mode in each of the three
programmable layers, and this allowed you to freely remap keys. Unfortunately,
this made it well difficult to share layouts, and made extensive remapping
rather unwieldy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="http://www.vortexgear.tw/db/upload/webdata4/6vortex_201861271445393.exe">updated firmware&lt;/a> (&amp;quot;&lt;code>CORE_MPC&lt;/code>&amp;quot;) does away with the hardware
programming, and instead introduces both a web UI for generating keyboard
layouts and a simple mechanism for pushing those layouts to the keyboard that
is completely operating system independent (which is nice if you&amp;rsquo;re a Linux
user and are tired of having to spin up a Windows VM just to run someone&amp;rsquo;s
firmware programming tool). With the new firmware, you hold down &lt;code>Fn-d&lt;/code> when
booting the keyboard and it will present a FAT-format volume to the operating
system. Drag your layout to the volume, unmount it, and reboot the keyboard and
you&amp;rsquo;re all set (note that you will still need to spin up that Windows VM
one last time in order to install the firmware update).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Vortexgear keyboard configurator is available at
&lt;a href="http://www.vortexgear.tw/mpc/index.html">http://www.vortexgear.tw/mpc/index.html&lt;/a>, but you&amp;rsquo;re going to want to use
&lt;a href="https://tsfreddie.github.io/much-programming-core/">https://tsfreddie.github.io/much-programming-core/&lt;/a> instead, which removes
several limitations that are present in the official tool.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because the new configurator (a) allows you to remap all layers, including
layer 0, and (b) allows to create mappings for the &lt;code>Pn&lt;/code> key, you have a lot
of flexibility in how you set up your mappings.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-ive-configured-things">How I&amp;rsquo;ve configured things&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I performed some limited remapping of layer 0:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve moved the &lt;code>Fn1&lt;/code> key to the right space bar, and turned the original
&lt;code>Fn1&lt;/code> key into the quote key. I use that enough in general writing that
it&amp;rsquo;s convenient to be able to access it without using a modifier.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve set up a cursor cluster using the &lt;code>Pn&lt;/code> key. This gets me the
standard &lt;code>WASD&lt;/code> keys for arrows, and &lt;code>Q&lt;/code> and &lt;code>E&lt;/code> for page up and page
down.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Holding down the &lt;code>Pn&lt;/code> key also gets me a numeric keypad on the right side
of the keyboard.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a fun keyboard. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure it&amp;rsquo;s going to become my primary keyboard,
especially for writing code, but I&amp;rsquo;m definitely happy with it.&lt;/p></content></item><item><title>Some thoughts on Mechanical Keyboards</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2020-04-15-some-thoughts-on-mechanical-ke/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2020-04-15-some-thoughts-on-mechanical-ke/</guid><description>Since we&amp;rsquo;re all stuck in the house and working from home these days, I&amp;rsquo;ve had to make some changes to my home office. One change in particular was requested by my wife, who now shares our rather small home office space with me: after a week or so of calls with me clattering away on my old Das Keyboard 3 Professional in the background, she asked if I could get something that was maybe a little bit quieter.</description><content>&lt;p>Since we&amp;rsquo;re all stuck in the house and working from home these days, I&amp;rsquo;ve had to make some changes to my home office. One change in particular was requested by my wife, who now shares our rather small home office space with me: after a week or so of calls with me clattering away on my old Das Keyboard 3 Professional in the background, she asked if I could get something that was maybe a little bit quieter.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I didn&amp;rsquo;t really need much of a push: I have a &lt;a href="https://www.coolermaster.com/catalog/peripheral/keyboards/masterkeys-s-with-superior-pbt-keycaps/">Cooler Master MasterKeys S&lt;/a> at $work with Cherry MX brown switches that I like a lot, and I would have just bought that one but Cooler Master has stopped manufacturing it. I thought about buying a new Das Keyboard, but their support is awful: while my Das Keyboard 3 Professional has worked fine for many years, I also owned a 4C that stopped working after about a year, and they wanted to charge me $80 just to look at it. You&amp;rsquo;re better off putting that money towards a nicer keyboard from somewhere else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in the &lt;a href="https://qmk.fm/">QMK&lt;/a> project &amp;ndash; an open source keyboard firmware with all sorts of nifty features &amp;ndash; for a while, but it turns out that there aren&amp;rsquo;t many &amp;ldquo;off the shelf&amp;rdquo; mechanical keyboards with standard layouts that can be used with QMK firmware. The folks at &lt;a href="https://drop.com/">Drop&lt;/a> market a few models that &lt;em>do&lt;/em> support QMK, so I gave the &lt;a href="https://drop.com/buy/drop-ctrl-mechanical-keyboard">Drop CTRL&lt;/a> a shot. TL;DR: It&amp;rsquo;s a fine keyboard, but it turns out I really have no need for RGB lighting. The translucent key labels just mean I can&amp;rsquo;t see them well in bright light, and mostly the lights were just distracting. I also found that with the low profile case I was constantly hitting the &amp;ldquo;windows&amp;rdquo; key with my palm, which was annoying. Playing with QMK was fun, but I ended up sending the CTRL back.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="left" >
&lt;img src="https://blog.oddbit.com/assets/2020/04/15/drop-ctrl.png" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m now using a &lt;a href="https://amazon.com/DURGOD-Mechanical-Interface-Tenkeyless-Anti-Ghosting/dp/B078H3WPHM?">Durgod K320 Taurus&lt;/a>, also with Cherry MX brown switches. I&amp;rsquo;m much happier with this keyboard: it is as expected very similar to the Masterkeys S I&amp;rsquo;ve been using. It feels very solid and it has a detachable cable, which seems trivial until your cats gnaws on it and your keyboard stops working. While the keyboard does support some customization, the software to take advantage of that tragically only runs under Windows, so I&amp;rsquo;m using it without any bells and whistles right now. It&amp;rsquo;s been great so far, and the price is very reasonable (especially compared to the CTRL).&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="left" >
&lt;img src="https://blog.oddbit.com/assets/2020/04/15/durgod-k320.png" />
&lt;/figure></content></item></channel></rss>