<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Review on blog.oddbit.com</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/review/</link><description>Recent content in Review on blog.oddbit.com</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Lars Kellogg-Stedman</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 12:29:07 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/review/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A review of the Garmin Fenix 6(x)</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2023-02-15-garmin-fenix-6/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2023-02-15-garmin-fenix-6/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been using a &lt;a href="https://www.garmin.com/en-US/p/641435"&gt;Garmin Fenix 6x&lt;/a&gt; for a couple of weeks and thought it might be interesting to put together a short review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="is-it-really-a-smartwatch"&gt;Is it really a smartwatch?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s a misnomer to call the Fenix a &amp;ldquo;smartwatch&amp;rdquo;. I would call it a highly capable fitness tracker. That&amp;rsquo;s not a knock on the product; I really like it so far, but pretty much everything it does is centered around either fitness tracking or navigation. If you browse around the &lt;a href="https://apps.garmin.com/en-US/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Connect IQ&amp;rdquo; store&lt;/a&gt;, mostly you&amp;rsquo;ll find (a) watch faces, (b) fitness apps, and (c) navigation apps. It&amp;rsquo;s not able to control your phone (for the most part; there are some apps available that offer remote camera control and some other limited features); you can&amp;rsquo;t check your email on it, or send text messages, and you&amp;rsquo;ll never find a watch version of any major smartphone app.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Grove Beginner Kit for Arduino (part 2): First look</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2020-06-07-first-look-seed-grove-beginner/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2020-06-07-first-look-seed-grove-beginner/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The folks at &lt;a href="https://seeedstudio.com"&gt;Seeed Studio&lt;/a&gt; were kind enough to send me a &lt;a href="https://www.seeedstudio.com/Grove-Beginner-Kit-for-Arduino-p-4549.html"&gt;Grove
Beginner Kit for Arduino&lt;/a&gt; for review. That&amp;rsquo;s a mouthful of a name
for a compact little kit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Grove Beginner Kit for Arduino (henceforth &amp;ldquo;the Kit&amp;rdquo;, because ain&amp;rsquo;t
nobody got time to type that out more than a few times in a single
article) is about 8.5 x 5 x 1 inches. Closed, you could fit two of
them on a piece of 8.5x11 paper with a little room leftover.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Fring: How not to handle registration</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2010-01-24-fring-how-not-to-handle-regist/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2010-01-24-fring-how-not-to-handle-regist/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I thought I&amp;rsquo;d give Fring a try after seeing some favorable reviews on other sites. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t previously heard of Fring, the following blurb from their website might be helpful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using your handset&amp;rsquo;s internet connection, you can interact with friends on all your favourite social networks including Skype, MSN Messenger, Google Talk, ICQ, SIP, Twitter, Yahoo! and AIM. You can listen to music with your Last.fm friends, check out what each other are up to on Facebook, receive alerts of new Google Mail and tailor make your very own fring by adding more cool experiences from fringAdd-ons&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>