<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Faa on blog.oddbit.com</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/faa/</link><description>Recent content in Faa on blog.oddbit.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Lars Kellogg-Stedman</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/faa/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>FAA Cannot Require Drone Registration</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2017-05-25-faa-cannot-require-drone-regis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2017-05-25-faa-cannot-require-drone-regis/</guid><description>This is now old news if you&amp;rsquo;re already following the drone industry, but if you&amp;rsquo;re not, I&amp;rsquo;d like to highlight a recent decision made by the US Court of Appeals regarding the FAA&amp;rsquo;s drone registration requirements.
To place this in context, back in 2015 the FAA established a new set of regulations (the &amp;ldquo;Registration Rule&amp;rdquo;) requiring anyone with a UAV (&amp;ldquo;unmanned aerial vehicle&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;drone&amp;rdquo;) weighing between 0.5 and 55 lbs to register with the FAA.</description><content>&lt;p>This is now old news if you&amp;rsquo;re already following the drone industry,
but if you&amp;rsquo;re not, I&amp;rsquo;d like to highlight a recent decision made by the
US Court of Appeals regarding the FAA&amp;rsquo;s drone registration
requirements.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To place this in context, back in 2015 the FAA established a new set
of regulations (the &amp;ldquo;Registration Rule&amp;rdquo;) requiring anyone with a UAV
(&amp;ldquo;unmanned aerial vehicle&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;drone&amp;rdquo;) weighing between 0.5 and 55
lbs to register with the FAA. Unfortunately, the 2012 &lt;a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/112th-congress/house-bill/658/text">FAA
Modernization and Reform Act says&lt;/a> says (in section 336(a)):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In General&amp;hellip;the Administrator of the Federal Aviation
Administration may not promulgate any rule or regulation regarding
a model aircraft, or an aircraft being developed as a model
aircraft&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>John Taylor, a hobbiest in Washington, D.C, challenged the new
registration regulations in court and was handed a clear victory.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.cadc.uscourts.gov/internet/opinions.nsf/FA6F27FFAA83E20585258125004FBC13/%24file/15-1495-1675918.pdf">The Court of Appeals decision&lt;/a> boils down to &amp;ldquo;when the law says
you &amp;lsquo;may not promulgate any rule regarding model aircraft&amp;rsquo;, that
means&amp;hellip;&amp;lsquo;you may not promulgate any rule regarding model aircraft&amp;rsquo;.
The decision is interesting in its simplicity. There is no arguing
about legal nuance here; it&amp;rsquo;s a clear case of the Court telling the
FAA &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;re wrong&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following quote from the decision really sums that up (highlights
are mine):&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In short, the 2012 FAA Modernization and Reform Act provides that
the FAA “may not promulgate any rule or regulation regarding a model
aircraft,” yet the FAA’s 2015 Registration Rule is a “rule or
regulation regarding a model aircraft.” &lt;strong>Statutory interpretation
does not get much simpler.&lt;/strong> The Registration Rule is unlawful as
applied to model aircraft.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The FAA attempted to describe the registration requirements as simply
a &amp;ldquo;reinterpretation&amp;rdquo; of existing rules. That is, they claimed to be
using their discretion to apply an existing registration rule for
&amp;ldquo;aircraft&amp;rdquo; in general to model aircraft:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Specifically, the FAA notes that, under longstanding statutes,
aircraft are statutorily required to register before operation.
&amp;hellip;But the FAA has never previously interpreted that registration
requirement to apply to model aircraft. The FAA responds that
nothing in the 2012 FAA Modernization and Reform Act prevents the
FAA from changing course and applying that registration requirement
to model aircraft now.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The Court disagreed with this characterization in no uncertain terms:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>We disagree. The Registration Rule does not merely announce an
intent to enforce a pre-existing statutory requirement. The
Registration Rule is a rule that creates a new regulatory regime for
model aircraft. The new regulatory regime includes a “new
registration process” for online registration of model
aircraft&amp;hellip;The new regulatory regime imposes new requirements – to
register, to pay fees, to provide information, and to display
identification on people who previously had no obligation to engage
with the FAA.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In short, the Registration Rule is a rule regarding model aircraft.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>And ultimately vacated the Registration Rule:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The FAA’s Registration Rule violates Section 336 of the FAA
Modernization and Reform Act. We grant Taylor’s petition for review
of the Registration Rule, and we vacate the Registration Rule to the
extent it applies to model aircraft.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Taylor also challenged the FAA&amp;rsquo;s flight restrictions in the
Washington, D.C. area, but lost that challenge on a technicality (&amp;ldquo;A
person seeking to challenge an FAA order must file the challenge
within 60 days of the order’s issuance.&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>