<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Kerberos on blog.oddbit.com</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/kerberos/</link><description>Recent content in Kerberos on blog.oddbit.com</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Lars Kellogg-Stedman</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 10:58:10 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/kerberos/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Mapping local users to Kerberos principals with SSSD</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2015-07-16-mapping-local-users-to-kerbero/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2015-07-16-mapping-local-users-to-kerbero/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I work for an organization that follows the common model of assigning
people systematically generated user ids. Like most technically
inclined employees of this organization, I have local accounts on my
workstation that don&amp;rsquo;t bear any relation to the generated account ids.
For the most part this isn&amp;rsquo;t a problem, except that our organization
uses Kerberos to authenticate access to a variety of resources (such
as the mailserver and a variety of web applications).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Kerberos authenticated queries to Active Directory</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2010-06-29-linux-kerberos-ad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2010-06-29-linux-kerberos-ad/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are many guides out there to help you configure your Linux system as an LDAP and Kerberos client to an Active Directory server. Most of these guides solve the problem of authentication by embedding a username and password into a configuration file somewhere on your system. While this works, it presents some problems:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you use a common account for authentication from all of your Linux systems, a compromise on one system means updating the configuration of all of your systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to use a common account, you need to provision a new account for each computer&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;which is silly, because if you join the system to Active Directory there is already a computer object associated with the system that can be used for authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This document describes how to configure a Linux system such that queries
generated by &lt;a href="http://www.padl.com/OSS/nss_ldap.html"&gt;nss_ldap&lt;/a&gt; will use either the current user&amp;rsquo;s Kerberos
credentials, or, for the root user, credentials stored in a Kerberos
credentials cache.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>