<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cloud-Init on blog.oddbit.com</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/cloud-init/</link><description>Recent content in Cloud-Init on blog.oddbit.com</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>Lars Kellogg-Stedman</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 10:58:10 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.oddbit.com/tags/cloud-init/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>OpenStack Networking without DHCP</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2015-06-26-openstack-networking-without-d/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2015-06-26-openstack-networking-without-d/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In an OpenStack environment, &lt;a href="https://cloudinit.readthedocs.org/en/latest/"&gt;cloud-init&lt;/a&gt; generally fetches
information from the metadata service provided by Nova. It also has
support for reading this information from a &lt;em&gt;configuration drive&lt;/em&gt;,
which under OpenStack means a virtual CD-ROM device attached to your
instance containing the same information that would normally be
available via the metadata service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is possible to generate your network configuration from this
configuration drive, rather than relying on the DHCP server provided
by your OpenStack environment. In order to do this you will need to
make the following changes to your Nova configuration:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Booting cloud images with libvirt</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2015-03-10-booting-cloud-images-with-libv/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2015-03-10-booting-cloud-images-with-libv/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Most major distributions now provide &amp;ldquo;cloud-enabled&amp;rdquo; images designed
for use in cloud environments like OpenStack and AWS. These images
are usually differentiated by (a) being relatively small, and (b) running
&lt;a href="http://cloudinit.readthedocs.org/"&gt;cloud-init&lt;/a&gt; at boot to perform initial system configuration tasks
using metadata provided by the cloud environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of their small size and support for automatic configuration
(including such useful tasks as provisioning ssh keys), these images
are attractive for use &lt;em&gt;outside&lt;/em&gt; of a cloud environment.
Unfortunately, when people first try to boot them they are met with
frustration as first the image takes forever to boot as it tries to
contact a non-existent metadata service, and then when it finally does
boot they are unable to log in because the images typically only
support key-based login.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>