<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>coronavirus on blog.oddbit.com</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/tag/coronavirus/</link><description>Recent content in coronavirus on blog.oddbit.com</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Lars Kellogg-Stedman</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://blog.oddbit.com/tag/coronavirus/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>You can't get an N95 mask: Now what?</title><link>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2020-07-28-you-cant-get-an-n95-mask-now-w/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://blog.oddbit.com/post/2020-07-28-you-cant-get-an-n95-mask-now-w/</guid><description>[This is a guest post by my partner Alexandra van Geel.]
TL;DR Hello everyone! The Basics: Masks vs. Respirators Question: What makes a good mask? Commercially available options The O2 Canada Curve Respirator The Vogmask valveless mask Some tips about comfort References Disclaimer: I am not an expert, just a private individual summarizing available information. Please correct me if I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten something wrong.
TL;DR I suggest: (a) the Vogmask valveless mask or (b) the O2 Canada Curve Respirator.</description><content>&lt;p>[This is a guest post by my partner Alexandra van Geel.]&lt;/p>
&lt;nav id="TableOfContents">
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#tldr">TL;DR&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#hello-everyone">Hello everyone!&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#the-basics-masks-vs-respirators">The Basics: Masks vs. Respirators&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#question-what-makes-a-good-mask">Question: What makes a good mask?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#commercially-available-options">Commercially available options&lt;/a>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#the-o2-canada-curve-respirator">The O2 Canada Curve Respirator&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#the-vogmask-valveless-mask">The Vogmask valveless mask&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#some-tips-about-comfort">Some tips about comfort&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#references">References&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/nav>
&lt;p>Disclaimer: I am not an expert, just a private individual summarizing available
information. Please correct me if I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten something wrong.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tldr">TL;DR&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>I suggest: (a) the &lt;a href="https://www.vogmask.com/collections/all">Vogmask valveless mask&lt;/a> or (b) the &lt;a href="https://o2canada.com/products/o2-curve-1-2">O2 Canada Curve
Respirator&lt;/a>. If (b), make sure you cut some an extra filter into two small
circles and put the material in the respirator to cover the exhale valves.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>If you use a homemade cloth mask, pick one that lets you get a good seal all
around. Use one with a pocket for a filter &amp;ndash; preferably, one made out of
polypropylene.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>If you use a disposable surgical-style mask, alter it to get at tighter fit,
like &lt;a href="HTTPS://www.tiktok.com/@oliviacuidmd/video/6841373365500955909">this&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="hello-everyone">Hello everyone!&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending an absurd amount of time researching masks. Motivated by
love for my family and &amp;ndash; let&amp;rsquo;s face it &amp;ndash; enjoyment of small research
projects, I decided to develop an informed set of recommendations to share. I
wanted to make sure that my recommendations were evidence-based and reflected
practicality, including wearability and availability, at least as of the time
of writing. This document is the result. Let&amp;rsquo;s get started.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-basics-masks-vs-respirators">The Basics: Masks vs. Respirators&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To begin, I wanted to understand some of the terms that have been thrown around
from &amp;ldquo;face coverings&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;surgical&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;medical&amp;rdquo; masks and of course
respirators including the gold standard (in the United States), the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N95_mask">N95&lt;/a> (so
called because it filters out at least 95% of airborn particles). Most of these
labels are common English terms yet have specific technical meanings, which
I&amp;rsquo;ve summarized below.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>Sources:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/npptl/pdfs/UnderstandDifferenceInfographic-508.pdf">https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/npptl/pdfs/UnderstandDifferenceInfographic-508.pdf&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.astm.org/standardization-news/?q=features/standards-medical-face-masks-and-protective-clothing-.html">https://www.astm.org/standardization-news/?q=features/standards-medical-face-masks-and-protective-clothing-.html&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The bottom line is that for the wearer, NIOSH-approved respirators provide the
highest level of protection against viruses. Both surgical/medical masks and
other face coverings provide less protection due to a combination of loose fit
and different filtration ability of the material.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As we all know by now, N95 masks are in short supply and should be reserved for
front-line medical personnel. So what&amp;rsquo;s the best alternative? Keep reading!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="question-what-makes-a-good-mask">Question: What makes a good mask?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Answer: primarily, protectiveness and breathability. The difficulty is that
each one often comes at the expense of the other.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> N95 masks are made out of a
nonwoven synthetic material that must meet regulatory criteria relating to
protectiveness and breathability, but how do other materials compare? More
specifically, I sought quantitative information on:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Differential pressure / airflow resistance&lt;/em>, which are measures of
breathability. Lower values are better.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Filtration efficiency&lt;/em> (e.g., for viruses, for bacteria, and/or for particles
of a particular size range), which are measures of protectiveness. Expressed
as a percentage, higher values are better.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Before describing test results for other materials, I offer two cautions.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>First, test conditions matter. Filtration efficiency is a function of both
particle size and airflow rates. A filtration test using larger particle
sizes will produce a higher filtration rate than will an otherwise identical
test using smaller particles. Also, a filtration test using a lower airflow
rate will produce a numerically higher filtration efficiency value, all else
equal. To make sure that regulated masks and respirators meet safety
standards, NIOSH and FDA require the use of specific standard operating
protocols in their respirator/mask testing. In contrast, testing efforts
undertaken by third-party laboratories or researchers may use different
protocols, and it is therefore important to carefully review the testing
methods to appropriately interpret the results.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>My second caution is that in practice, mask protectiveness depends not only
on the filtration ability of the material itself but also on fit. Some
research focuses only on the properties of the material and not on how well
any particular mask made from the materials, might or might not fit. A mask
made of the best material in the world will provide limited protection if it
does not fit securely.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>With that out of the way, let&amp;rsquo;s look at the &amp;ldquo;gold standard&amp;rdquo; N95, as other
materials are typically compared to its performance. The &amp;ldquo;N95 FFR designation
is determined by the CDC&amp;rsquo;s National Institute for Occupational Safety and
Health (&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/niosh/index.htm">NIOSH&lt;/a>) and indicates a minimum filtration of 95% for particle sizes
0.022−0.259 μm (count median diameter of 0.075 ± 0.02 μm), according to 42 Code
of Federal Regulations (CFR) &lt;a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=fdd4020598032b884cbca81cf64c8986&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=pt42.1.84&amp;amp;rgn=div5#se42.1.84_110">Part 84.10&lt;/a>. As the [COVID-19] viral aerosols are
larger than the ~0.120 μm virus itself, N95 respirators are expected to provide
suitable protection&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.nanolett.0c02211">Zhao et al. 2020&lt;/a>).&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In short, to be certified by NIOSH, an N95 candidate must pass a specific
filtration efficiency test, which is performed using a charge-neutralized NaCl
aerosol (&lt;a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=fdd4020598032b884cbca81cf64c8986&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=pt42.1.84&amp;amp;rgn=div5#se42.1.84_1174">42 CFR §84.174&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Until very recently, there was almost no filtration efficiency or differential
pressure information for more common materials. I speculate that prior to the
current pandemic, few studies had examined the protectiveness of cloth or
surgical-style medical masks because there seemed little point: in countries
with more money to devote to research, N95 masks were sufficiently plentiful
that there was little incentive to consider what the runner-up might be. Of
course, that situation has now changed, and the table below,&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> I&amp;rsquo;ve identified
three studies &amp;ndash; all from 2020 &amp;ndash; that attempt to answer these questions. Each
study used a different study design and examined different household materials.
All the studies included N95 masks for comparative purposes. This is important
particularly as the filtration efficiency testing protocols employed are not
identical to those required under &lt;a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=fdd4020598032b884cbca81cf64c8986&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=pt42.1.84&amp;amp;rgn=div5#se42.1.84_110">42 CFR §84.10&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>It is notable that the results from these three studies do not all align: &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acsnano.0c03252">Konda
et al. (2020)&lt;/a> found common materials to have a notably greater filter
efficiency (up to 97%!) than did the other two studies. &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsnano.0c05025">Zangmeister et al.
(2020)&lt;/a> points this out directly: &amp;ldquo;Combinations of cotton and
synthetic fabrics identical, or nearly identical, to those outlined in Konda et
al. were tested here, and the present results were not consistent with the
prior findings.&amp;rdquo; Particularly given N95 masks are made from specialized (as
opposed to common) materials, I have a low level of confidence in the high
filtration efficiency of common materials reported in &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acsnano.0c03252">Konda et al.
(2020)&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In contrast to the results of &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acsnano.0c03252">Konda et al. (2020)&lt;/a>, the other two
publications suggest that the tested fabrics alone or in combination generally
have a filtration efficiency of below 50%, possibly substantially below. The
filtration efficiency of surgical mask material was similar to the upper end of
the range of that measured in more common materials. Certain polypropylene
materials (a multi-layer HEPA filter and medical-grade wrap) fared better, with
filtration efficiencies of approximately 75% and higher (&lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsnano.0c05025">Zangmeister et al.
2020&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The breathability of the common materials varied. Overall, multiple layers
provided more filtration efficiency but also reduced breathability. For
instance, &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsnano.0c05025">Zangmeister et al. (2020)&lt;/a> found that increasing
the number of layers of a cotton poplin weave monotonically increased the
filtration efficiency; however, more than four layers &amp;ldquo;exceeded the NIOSH
recommended ΔP [pressure differential] during exhalation through a fitted mask
(245.2 Pa, 25 mm H2O)&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In short, as others have observed, a mask made from common fabrics is better
than no mask at all, but in protectiveness are still substantially inferior to
the N95. Breathability was highly variable depending on the material and number
of layers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="commercially-available-options">Commercially available options&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My hope, when starting this review, was to either find reassurance about the
protectiveness of a homemade mask or to find an available product that I could
be convinced was reasonably protective (based on evidence rather than
marketing!) and tolerable. More specifically, I sought products with
documented results of laboratory testing of filtration and breathability. The
two best candidates I found are described below. (If anyone finds other
excellent options, please let me know!)&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-o2-canada-curve-respirator">The O2 Canada Curve Respirator&lt;/h3>
&lt;figure class="left" >
&lt;img src="curve-sideview.png" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="specs">Specs&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Filter material&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Technostat® 150 by Superior Felt &amp;amp; Filtration&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Bacterial partical efficiency&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Filter material &amp;gt;99.9992% (Nelson Labs Spec MIL-M-36954C)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Viral particle efficiency&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Filter material &amp;gt;99.997% (Nelson Labs Spec MIL-M-36954C)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Filter material &amp;gt;99.997% (NaCl neutralized aerosol, at 236 LPM) (LMS
Technologies Inc. IEST-RP-CC001.6)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Pressure drop (airflow)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;lt;1.1 mm (&amp;lt;11 Pa, at 32 LPM) (Nelson Labs Exhalation Resistance Test
TEB-APR-STP-0003)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>0.217 mm (2.1 Pa, at 236 LPM) (LMS Technologies Inc. IEST-RP-CC001.6)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Fit test&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Passed (ACUTE Environmental &amp;amp;Safety Services CSA Z94.4-2011)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Notes&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hard shell. One size but two models for high/low nose bridge fits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Includes exhalation valve (i.e., does not protect others unless you cover the
valves with extra filter material).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“N95 is based on passing three tests looking at valve leakage, breathability,
and a load test. O2 Curve has passed two of these tests at Nelson Labs, but
due to the compact nature of our filter it is not compatible with the load
testing procedure. The filter simply doesn&amp;rsquo;t have enough surface area to pass
the test” (&lt;a href="https://o2canada.com/blogs/official-statements/ceo-letter-20200218">CEO letter&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>(The above information is from the &lt;a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1056/9620/files/O2_Curve_Performance_Research_Summary_2.pdf">O2 Curve Performance Research Summary&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="review">Review&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://o2canada.com/products/o2-curve-1-2">O2 Canada Curve Respirator&lt;/a> consists of a two-layer hard shell with a
replaceable filter inserted between the inner and outer layers, and with
silicone around the edges to achieve a better seal to the face. The advantage
of a hard shell is that the respirator will not collapse against your face when
breathing hard. A potential disadvantage is that, given its generally rigid
structure, the shape may not match your facial structure well enough to seal
properly. Unfortunately, the only way to know if it fits and is comfortable is
to buy one and try it out. My parents did this, and my mother found it to fit
well, but my father did not. Because this mask is both expensive and not
returnable, acquiring one represents something of a financial risk. As a final
note about fit, I will mention that this respirator is available in only one
size but in two shapes, intended for different nose bridges.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The key advantage of this product &amp;ndash; originally developed for the Asian market
as a respirator for use in polluted areas &amp;ndash; is its filter. This filter
material is a product called Technostat® 150. O2 Canada&amp;rsquo;s website &lt;a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1056/9620/files/O2_Curve_Performance_Research_Summary_2.pdf">includes the
results of independent third-party testing&lt;/a> of their masks, and the material
itself is intended for medical-grade purposes, as indicated &lt;a href="https://www.superiorfelt.com/products/air-filtration-media/sub-micron/personal-protection/">on the
manufacturer&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a>. The filter is also exceptionally breathable &amp;ndash; test
results aside, my mother reported that it was much better than our homemade
cloth masks in that regard. The table below summarizes the presented test
results for this filter both with respect to filtration efficacy and pressure
drop (breathability).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A key disadvantage of this product is that &lt;em>as provided&lt;/em>, &lt;em>it will not similarly
protect those around you because it has built-in exhalation valves not covered
by the filter&lt;/em>. These values make exhaling easier (and are consistent with the
mask&amp;rsquo;s original purpose, which is use in areas with polluted air); however, for
COVID purposes, it&amp;rsquo;s best to protect not only yourself but also others.
Fortunately, due to the mask&amp;rsquo;s design, it is possible to cut out pieces of the
filter material and put them over the valves, which should help prevent
unfiltered breath from leaking out; however, this is my own speculation and has
not been evaluated by any lab test. In the future, the company may make filter
inserts that cover the valves, but such pre-cut filters are not presently
available.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-vogmask-valveless-mask">The Vogmask valveless mask&lt;/h3>
&lt;figure class="left" >
&lt;img src="vogmask.jpg" />
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="specs-1">Specs&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Filter material&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No filter brand specified.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Bacterial partical efficiency&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0250/0840/files/Nelson_Labs_Bacterial_Filtering_1112599-S01.pdf?8699031093377030261">&amp;gt;99.9%&lt;/a> (Nelson Labs)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>mean particle size (MPS) of 3.0 um ± 0.3 um&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Viral particle efficiency&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0250/0840/files/Nelson_Labs_Viral_Filtration_1112598-S01.pdf?8699031093377030261">&amp;gt;99.9%&lt;/a> (Nelson Labs, mean particle size (MPS) of 3.0 um ± 0.3 um)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0250/0840/files/Nelson_Labs_Particl_Penetrations_NaCl_1101889-S01.pdf?8699031093377030261">Conforms to the NIOSH N95 criteria for filter efficiency&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Pressure drop (airflow)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/0250/0840/files/Nelson_Labs_Inhalation_Exhalation_1101891-S01.pdf?8699031093377030261">Conforms to NIOSH criteria for N95 pretesting&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Fit test&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not reported&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Notes&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Filter sewn into mask; not replaceable&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fabric-based&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.vogmask.com/pages/technical">https://www.vogmask.com/pages/technical&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="review-1">Review&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Vogmask also originally developed masks for people wishing to reduce
exposure to pollutants. Consistent with that purpose, some Vogmasks do have
valves; however, the company has now introduced a line of masks that lacks
valves. The &lt;a href="https://www.vogmask.com/collections/all">Vogmask valveless mask&lt;/a> is fabric-based and, while stiffer than the typical
homemade mask, still has the potential to collapse inward against one&amp;rsquo;s
mouth/nose under conditions of heavy breathing. Fit is, however, not likely to
be a problem: not only does the mask have a nosepiece to allow for a customized
fit, it also comes in multiple sizes intended for children through large
adults.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A potential disadvantage is that this mask&amp;rsquo;s filter is sewn-in and
non-replaceable. As such, the manufacturer states that the entire mask must be
replaced from time to time. It can be hand-washed, but the instructions note
that this will clean only the outside layers, and the inner filter will not be
effectively cleaned. The company provides some estimates of how long the
filter may last, but these will undoubtedly vary depending on frequency and
duration of use, as well as the conditions of use.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Both my kids have preferred the Vogmask over the O2 Canada Curve respirator (I
cannot swear it wasn&amp;rsquo;t appearance rather than fit or breathability that drove
their preference…). Vogmask availability has unfortunately been limited. This
would tend to eliminate it as a practical option(!) except that they seem to be
able to regularly replenish their stock: within a few days, the website
announces a new day and time for availability of additional masks, usually
about a week later. Whether this pattern will continue is anyone&amp;rsquo;s guess, but
if you&amp;rsquo;re interested, I&amp;rsquo;d advise keeping an eye on their website then marking
that day/time on your calendar and be ready to place your order immediately.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="some-tips-about-comfort">Some tips about comfort&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re in a situation where you have to wear a mask for a long period of
time, comfort is key and all the more so for kids. (If they&amp;rsquo;re taking it off
because they can&amp;rsquo;t stand it, it won&amp;rsquo;t be protective, however great its specs
might be!) So here are some possible solutions to two common problems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Fabric collapse&lt;/strong>. I&amp;rsquo;ve found one tool that may help some people with
fabric-based masks by keeping the fabric away from directly touching the nose
and mouth: the 3D mask bracket. This forms a kind of frame on your face that
your mask sits on top of and holds in place. I can&amp;rsquo;t provide
specific recommendations about particular products, but there are a lot of
options (&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B08CR4NPP7/">for example&lt;/a>). With a little luck, you&amp;rsquo;ll find something that fits
your face reasonably well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Ear fatigue&lt;/strong>. Both of the masks I&amp;rsquo;ve suggested use ear loops. Ear loops may or
may not be comfortable for you, and if you use hearing aids, they are a
non-starter. Both O2 Canada and Vogmask offer solutions: the O2 Canada mask has
a &amp;ldquo;sport strap&amp;rdquo; (out of stock at the time of writing but anticipated back in
stock shortly), which goes around the head and neck. Vogmask sells a head strap
accessory (also sold out at the time of writing, but see prior text about their
pattern of restocking). In addition, there are many other third-party products
available to solve this problem &amp;ndash; try searching for phrases such as mask strap
extender, mask ear saver, and similar terms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s all, folks, and I hope it&amp;rsquo;s been useful! Stay safe.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Konda, A. Prakash, A. Moss, G. A., Schmoldt, M. Grant, G. D., and Guha, S.
2020. &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/acsnano.0c03252">Aerosol Filtration Efficiency of Common Fabrics Used in Respiratory
Cloth Masks&lt;/a>. ACS Nano 14: 6339−6347.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zangmeister, C. D., Radney, J. G., Vicenzi, E. P., and Weaver, J. L. 2020.
&lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acsnano.0c05025">Filtration Efficiencies of Nanoscale Aerosol by Cloth Mask Materials Used to
Slow the Spread of SARS-CoV‑2&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zhao, M. Liao, L., Xiao, W., Yu, X., Wang, H. Wang, Q. Lin, Y. L.,
Kilinc-Balci, F. S., Price, A., Chu, L., Chu, M. C., Chu, S., and Cui Y.
2020. &lt;a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.nanolett.0c02211">Household Materials Selection for Homemade Cloth Face Coverings and
Their Filtration Efficiency Enhancement&lt;/a>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>It also follows that the best mask for one purpose may not be the
best for all purposes: for instance, if you’re outside jogging, you may be
willing to sacrifice some degree of protectiveness for better access to fresh
air!&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>Other countries have their own promulgated standards for masks.
&lt;a href="https://multimedia.3m.com/mws/media/1791500O/comparison-ffp2-kn95-n95-filtering-facepiece-respirator-classes-tb.pdf">This document&lt;/a> is a useful reference for understanding the differences among
these standards.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>In some cases, I was unable to discern some of the study’s methods,
which is why there are some blank entries in this table.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></content></item></channel></rss>